{
  "reference_number": "10806",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This question is unclear; the government should set a 2050 target of net zero GhG emissions by 2050 now. Or the Government sets\n\n a goal to reach net zero emissions by 2050 and the CCC advises on specific emission budgets for the government later/asap."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Development aid should encourage support for other countries to develop carbon credits (and associated social and economic\n benefits) as well."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Politics du jour should not be allowed to change targets. A revision for stricter targets based on emerging science should be allowed."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "In addition, there should be a tentative emission 'budget' or trajectory all the way to 2050. This can be done through back casting\n\n based on plausible narratives derived from synthesis. These narratives / story lines should be the basis for improved analysis to allow\n for step changes beyond incremental projections."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Provided that the budget is ambitious in the short run and does not delay. It should provide a clear and steadfast message to\n\n business and society. The only reason to adjust the budget would be if scientific information (and the CCC) calls for faster and stricter\n budgets. Adjusting budgets equates to 'creative bookkeeping' and does not provide a clear indication on whether actions and\n outcomes are on track, compared to the budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Only if stricter budgets on a shorter time line are proposed."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The circumstances are not exceptional, but an artifact of an outdated economic approach. Update/future proof governmental\n\nsystems to become more agile and respond to these challenges in a more coherent manner. For example, 'fiscal circumstances and,\nin particular, the likely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing' and 'economic circumstances and, in\n\nparticular, the likely impact of the decision on the economy and the competitiveness of particular sectors of the economy' are typical\nexcuses that should NOT be allowed. The only competitive economy of the future IS a low GhG economy with characteristics of a\ncircular-, sharing-, ecological- and regenerative economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Targets and time frames are essential to give a clear signal to other sectors of society, so they can act accordingly."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "1. Start developing capacity in systems thinking, - design and - modelling. Neither Vivid or NZIER use systems based modelling\n(because it is hard) and therefore expose the decisions to systemic blind spots (i.e. unintended consequences and missed\n\nopportunities). 2. Start taking the Sustainable Development Goals more seriously. SDG#13 is Climate Action and interlinked with all\nother SDGs. After the low-hanging fruits regarding lowering emissions are exhausted, additional climate adaptation and mitigation can\n\nonly happen by taking the other SDGs into account."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Facilitate the connection/communication between local, regional and national government authorities for coherent climate mitigation\nand adaptation efforts."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Unclear question. See WISE RESPONSE submission for thoughtful suggestion."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "However, in addition to or instead of resource economists, perhaps consider Futurists, Scenario Planner, Sustainable Development\n\nexperts, Ecological Economists, Systems Thinkers/Designers and/or Communication experts."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Mitigation is the first priority. However, it will require systemic changes and can't be achieved without adaptation."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Please, add a detailed, multi-scalable National Land and Coastal Use / Management Plan."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Transparency is critical for credibility and could facilitate emerging solutions and partnerships, if done in an ethical, constructive and\nfair way."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Thank you for the opportunity to submit. Climate Change is one of the critical challenges we face to transition to a more sustainable\nand desirable society. I also wholeheartedly support the more elaborate submission by Wise Response."
    }
  ]
}
